<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--
~ Copyright (c) 2009, WSO2 Inc. (http://www.wso2.org) All Rights Reserved.
~
~ WSO2 Inc. licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
~ Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except
~ in compliance with the License.
~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
~
~ http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
~
~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
~ software distributed under the License is distributed on an
~ "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
~ KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the
~ specific language governing permissions and limitations
~ under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN"
      "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">
<head>
  <meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=iso-8859-1" />
  <title>WSO2 CEP Developer Guide</title>
  <link href="css/cep-docs.css" rel="stylesheet" />
  <link href="styles/dist-docs.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"
  media="all" />
</head>

<body>
<p>[<a href="docs_index.html">Documentation Index</a>] 
<h1>WSO2 CEP Developer Guide</h1>

<p>This guide is to demonstrate a simple Insurance Application which uses
business rules. </p>

<h2>Contents</h2>

<div class="toc">
<ul>
  <li><a href="#RuleEngineExecution">RuleEngineExecution</a> </li>
  <li><a href="#ProgrammingModel">ProgrammingModel</a> </li>
</ul>
</div>

<h2 id="RuleEngineExecution">RuleEngineExecution</h2>

<h3>Overall Design</h3>

<p>Intuitive Requirement: create facts, invoke the rule engine with the created
facts, and then process the results from the rule engine execution </p>

<p>Expected Quality Attributes: Functionality, Performance, Modifiability,
Re-Usability, Extensibility, and Conceptual Integrity </p>

<p><img src="images/rule-execution.png" alt="Rule Engine Execution" /> </p>

<p>In order to achieve a better performance, the rule engine execution was
divided into three main orthogonal functionalities. Each functionality can be
viewed as a separated stage or layer. <br />
Separating into stages or orthogonal functionalities is enabled to adopt
architectural styles such as SEDA, and Pipe and Filters, which are widely
acknowledged as architectural styles for achieving higher performance. For the
Pipe, and Filters, a stage is a filter and for a SEDA, it is a SEDA stage. <br
/>
Note: In the current implementation, we have not implemented any of above
strategies for achieving a better performance. </p>

<h3>Fact Adaptation</h3>

<p>Facts have been named as inputs and the Input Manager is responsible for
performing fact (input) adaptation. This stage is optional if the facts have
already been formulated. However, if the facts have to be formulated based on
the context in transit, the fact adaptation stage is required.</p>

<p><img src="images/fact-adapt.png" alt="Fact Adaptation" /> </p>

<p><strong>ResourceDescription</strong> Encapsulates the meta-data about both
facts/results. Furthermore, this can be used to capture any other configuration
information. For example, the adapter configuration in the
rule-component.conf</p>

<p><strong>Resource Adapter</strong> </p>
</p>
<pre>/**
 * Resources Adapter - This can be adapted input or output. It is needed to tell what can adapt
 * using OutputAdaptable, InputAdaptable , etc.
 */
public interface ResourceAdapter {
    
    /**
     * Type of  the resource that this adapter responsible for adapt. For an input, the type is the target type
     * for an output , it is a type of the source
     *
     * @return Resource type
     */
    String getType();
}
s</pre>

<p>

<p><strong>InputAdaptable</strong> To adapt a given object into a fact (input)
type that the adapter is responsible.</p>
</p>
<pre>/**
 * Adapts the given object based on the resource description. Note here that the given <strong>tobeAdapted</strong> is
 * data and only need to convert that into the correct target type.
 */
public interface InputAdaptable {

    /**
     * Converts provide object into the object type defined in the resource description
     *
     * @param resourceDescription Input ResourceDescription
     * @param tobeAdapted         The final calculated value ,
     *                            only need to convert that into correct type
     * @return Converted object representing expected type
     */
    Object adaptInput(ResourceDescription resourceDescription,
                      Object tobeAdapted);
}</pre>

<p>There are a few implementations</p>

<p><strong>POJOResourceAdapter </strong> Adapts a given object into a POJO</p>

<p><strong>MessageFactAdapter</strong> Adapts a given object into a Message</p>

<p><strong>DOMResorceAdapter</strong> Adapts a given object into a DOM node</p>

<p><strong>OMElementResorceAdapter </strong> Adapts a given object into a OM
Element</p>

<p>To get know who to registering new InputAdapters , please refer extending
BRS guide</p>

<p><strong>InputAdapterFactory</strong> - Create, Initiate and Manage Input
Adapters</p>

<p><strong>MessageInterceptor </strong> This is to access message being passed
between components in the system that rule component is used. When a BRS is
used as the mediator or the axis2 web service, facts have to be formulated
based on the message context objects. MessageInterceptor enables to decouple
the fact adaptation from the underlying system. There are two message
MessageInterceptor implementations : SynapseMessageInterceptor and
Axis2MessageInterceptor. The SynapseMessageInterceptor intercepts the synapse
message context whereas the Axis2MessageInterceptor intercepts the axis2
message context.</p>

<p><strong>InputAdaptationStrategy </strong>- Encapsulates an input Adaptation
algorithm or logic. This formulates the inputs based on description, adapters,
message interceptor, and context object.</p>

<p><h3>Rule Engine Invocation</h3>
</p>

<p>In order to invoke a rule engine, a session instance should be obtained. For
that purpose, RuleEngine can be used. How to obtain a RuleEngine will be
discussed in the Programming Model section. </p>

<p><img src="images/rule-invoke.png" alt="Rule Engine Invoke" /> </p>

<p><strong>RuleEngine</strong> is to proxy the actual rule engine provider. It
manages and controls the access to the rule engine provider. Actual rule engine
provider is encapsulated with RuleBackendRuntime, which provide simplified API
for accessing different rule engines, and allows plugging different rule
engine. In that sense, it is analog to JSR 94 API. However, RuleBackendRuntime
is simple and provide only functions required for the WSO2 BRS. It also
provides a way to use native rule engines' API based on the requirement
of WSO2 BRS. RuleBackendRuntime instance should be created only from
RuleBackendRuntimeFactory. RuleEngine is responsible for loading correct
RuleBackendRuntimeFactory and creating RuleBackendRuntime. Furthermore, it
proxies all method calls to RuleBackendRuntime and do parameter and return
value validation. Therefore, users must only access the rule engine provider
through RuleEngine not from the RuleBackendRuntime.</p>

<p><strong>RuleBackendRuntime</strong></p>

<p>/**</p>

<p>* Encapsulates the rule service provider or the engine implements a rule
engine. This adapts an</p>

<p>* existing rule engine implementation.</p>

<p>* &lt;p/&gt;</p>

<p>* This class exposes functionality required to create a rule execution set,
a session associated</p>

<p>* with a rule execution set and remove a registered execution set.
Furthermore, this provide a</p>

<p>* way to destroy underlying rule engine.</p>

<p>*/</p>

<p>public interface RuleBackendRuntime {</p>

<p></p>

<p>/**</p>

<p>* Registers a rule set. The rule set should be given in the
RuleSetDescription as the rule source.</p>

<p>* Within this method , an executable rule set is created and registered with
the rule engine</p>

<p>*</p>

<p>* @param description information about the rule set</p>

<p>* @return Registered URI of the rule set</p>

<p>*/</p>

<p>public String addRuleSet(RuleSetDescription description);</p>

<p></p>

<p>/**</p>

<p>* Create a session based on the given SessionDescription. The session can be
stateful or stateless</p>

<p>*</p>

<p>* @param sessionDescription information about the session to be created</p>

<p>* @return a valid &lt;code&gt;Session&lt;/code&gt; object, either stateful
or stateless</p>

<p>*/</p>

<p>public Session createSession(SessionDescription sessionDescription);</p>

<p></p>

<p>/**</p>

<p>* Removed a already registered rule set</p>

<p>*</p>

<p>* @param description information about the rule set to be removed</p>

<p>*/</p>

<p>public void removeRuleSet(RuleSetDescription description);</p>

<p></p>

<p>/**</p>

<p>* Cleanup any resources used by the rule engine</p>

<p>*/</p>

<p>public void destroy();</p>

<p>}</p>

<p></p>

<p><strong>RuleBackendRuntimeFactory</strong></p>
<pre xml:space="preserve">/**
 * A factory for creating a RuleBackendRuntime. This should provide a properly initiated
 * RuleBackendRuntime instance. It is recommended to use this class as the only means for creating
 * RuleBackendRuntime instances
 */
public interface RuleBackendRuntimeFactory {
    /**
     * Returns a  properly initiated RuleBackendRuntime instance.
     *
     * @param properties  properties to be used when creating the underlying rule service provider
     * @param classLoader class loader to be used by the underlying rule service provider to load
     *                    facts and other required classes
     * @return properly initiated &lt;code&gt;RuleBackendRuntime&lt;/code&gt;  instance if there are on exceptions.
     *         Otherwise, &lt;code&gt;LoggedRuntimeException/code&gt; should be thrown.
     */
    public RuleBackendRuntime createRuleBackendRuntime(Map&lt;String, PropertyDescription&gt; properties,
                                                       ClassLoader classLoader);
}</pre>

<p><strong>Session </strong>is the runtime connection between the rule engine
and its users.</p>
<pre xml:space="preserve">**
 * Runtime connection between the rule engine and its users
 */
public interface Session {

    /**
     * Execute the rule engine by providing inputs as a List of Objects
     *
     * @param facts facts as a list of objects
     * @return a list of results from the rule engine execution
     */
    List execute(List&lt;Object&gt; facts);

    /**
     * Releases the session
     */
    void release();
}</pre>

<p></p>

<h3>Results Adaptation</h3>

<p>Results adaptation process is almost similar to the fact adaptation process.
The difference is that the results adaptation deals with the results from the
rule engine invocation. Results are used to enrich the context object being
passed between components of the system uses the rule component. This stage is
also an optional. </p>

<p><img src="images/result-adapt.png" alt="Result Adaptation" /> </p>

<p><strong>Output Adaptable Interface</strong></p>
<pre xml:space="preserve">/**
 * Adapts a result based on output description. Before call for adapt ,
 * it is recommended to explicitly checks for whether result can be adapted or not
 */

public interface OutputAdaptable {

    /**
     * Adapts the result according to the corresponding output description. The result of adaptation
     * is put into the context based on the information in the output description.
     *
     * @param description        Output ResourceDescription
     * @param result             Result from the engine
     * @param context            the context to be used for looking up resources
     * @param messageInterceptor a helper class to locate resources from given context
     * @return True if Successfully adapt
     */
    boolean adaptOutput(ResourceDescription description,
                        Object result,
                        Object context,
                        MessageInterceptor messageInterceptor);

    /**
     * Explicitly checks for whether result can be adapted or not
     *
     * @param description Output ResourceDescription
     * @param output      Result from the engine
     * @return True if it is possible to successfully adapt
     */
    boolean canAdaptOutput(ResourceDescription description,
                           Object output);

    /**
     * Adapts the result according to the corresponding output description.
     *
     * @param description information about target object
     * @param result      the object to be adapted
     * @return Adapted Object
     */
    public Object adaptOutput(ResourceDescription description, Object result);
}</pre>

<h2 id="ProgrammingModel">Programming Model</h2>

<p>Rules component has exposed as an OSGI service. Therefore, the programming
model to adopt rules component is coupled to the OSGI service model. </p>

<h3>The OSGI Service </h3>

<p>RuleServerManagerService is the OSGI service interface for exposing rules
functionality. </p>
<pre xml:space="preserve">/**
 * RuleServerManagerService is to provide the functionality to create main components belong to the
 * rule server, and information belong to it. There are three main components
 * &lt;p/&gt;
 * &lt;ul&gt;
 * &lt;li&gt; Rule Engine
 * &lt;li&gt; Input Manager
 * &lt;li&gt; OutPut Manager
 * &lt;/ul&gt;
 * &lt;p/&gt;
 * Rule Engine encapsulates the underlying rule service provider. Input Manager is to adapt
 * given objects into target facts and OutPut Manager is to adapt results from the rule engine
 * into target objects
 */
public interface RuleServerManagerService {

    /**
     * Factory method to create a RuleEngine instance. This method returns a new RuleEngine instance.
     * The RuleEngine is created based on the RuleEngineProvider defined in the rule-component.conf
     *
     * @param ruleEngineClassLoader The class loader to be used by the RuleEngine instance
     * @return a valid &lt;code&gt;RuleEngine&lt;code&gt; instance
     */
    RuleEngine createRuleEngine(ClassLoader ruleEngineClassLoader);

    /**
     * Create an input manager instance based on the given input descriptions.
     *
     * @param inputs             A list of ResourceDescriptions presenting information abouts facts
     * @param messageInterceptor MessageInterceptor to be used for accessing the data in the message
     *                           being transit
     * @return a valid &lt;code&gt;InputManager &lt;/code&gt;  instance
     */
    InputManager createInputManager(List&lt;ResourceDescription&gt; inputs,
                                    MessageInterceptor messageInterceptor);

    /**
     * Create an output manager instance based on the given input descriptions.
     *
     * @param outputs            A list of ResourceDescriptions presenting information abouts results
     * @param messageInterceptor MessageInterceptor to be used for accessing the data in
     *                           the message being transit
     * @return a valid &lt;code&gt;OutputManager &lt;/code&gt;  instance
     */
    OutputManager createOutputManager(List&lt;ResourceDescription&gt; outputs,
                                      MessageInterceptor messageInterceptor);

    /**
     * Returns the InputAdapterFactory in the rule server. This is useful when it
     * is needed to access available input adapters and to add a new input adapter
     *
     * @return a valid &lt;code&gt;InputAdapterFactory&lt;/code&gt; instance
     */
    public InputAdapterFactory getFactAdapterFactory();

    /**
     * Returns the OutputAdapterFactory in the rule server. This is useful when it
     * is needed to access available result adapters and to add a new result adapter
     *
     * @return a valid &lt;code&gt;OutputAdapterFactory&lt;/code&gt; instance
     */
    public OutputAdapterFactory getResultAdapterFactory();
}</pre>

<h3>Integration Process</h3>

<p><strong>Step 1</strong> : Add an OSGI service reference and required maven
dependencies </p>
<pre xml:space="preserve">        * @scr.component name="ruleservices.component" immediate="true"
        * @scr.reference name="ruleservermanager.component"
        * interface="org.wso2.carbon.rule.server.RuleServerManagerService" cardinality="1..1"
        * policy="dynamic" bind="setRuleServerManagerService" unbind="unSetRuleServerManagerService"</pre>

<p></p>
<pre xml:space="preserve">    &lt;dependencies&gt;
        &lt;dependency&gt;
            &lt;groupId&gt;org.wso2.carbon&lt;/groupId&gt;
            &lt;artifactId&gt;org.wso2.carbon.rule.core&lt;/artifactId&gt;
            &lt;version&gt;3.0.0&lt;/version&gt;
        &lt;/dependency&gt;
        &lt;dependency&gt;
            &lt;groupId&gt;org.wso2.carbon&lt;/groupId&gt;
            &lt;artifactId&gt;org.wso2.carbon.rule.server&lt;/artifactId&gt;
            &lt;version&gt;3.0.0&lt;/version&gt;
        &lt;/dependency&gt;
        &lt;dependency&gt;
            &lt;groupId&gt;org.wso2.carbon&lt;/groupId&gt;
            &lt;artifactId&gt;org.wso2.carbon.rule.engine.drools&lt;/artifactId&gt;
            &lt;version&gt;3.0.0&lt;/version&gt;
        &lt;/dependency&gt;
        &lt;dependency&gt;
            &lt;groupId&gt;org.wso2.carbon&lt;/groupId&gt;
            &lt;artifactId&gt;org.wso2.carbon.rule.engine.jsr94&lt;/artifactId&gt;
            &lt;version&gt;3.0.0&lt;/version&gt;
        &lt;/dependency&gt;
    &lt;/dependencies&gt;
    </pre>

<p><strong>Step 2</strong> : Implementing MessageInterceptor</p>

<p>This step is optional and required if the facts should be formulated from a
message.</p>

<p>MessageInterceptor Interface</p>
<pre xml:space="preserve">/**
 * Provides an abstraction intercepting the context object being passed between components of
 * the system the rule component is used
 * &lt;p/&gt;
 * Provides required functionality to extractPayload data from the context and enrich the
 * context with some data.
 * &lt;p/&gt;
 * This enables to decouple the context message from the implementation of the rule component
 */
public interface MessageInterceptor {

    /**
     * Looking up for a resource with the given key. The look up processes is coupled to
     * the implementation
     *
     * @param key          an identifier to locate the resource
     * @param message      the context object being passed between components of
     *                     the system the rule component is used
     * @param defaultValue default value in the case of there is no resource for the given key
     * @return resorce corresponded to the given key if there is a resource for the give key.
     *         Otherwise, the default value should be returned
     */
    public ReturnValue extract(String key, Object message, Object defaultValue);

    /**
     * Looking up for a resource with the given XPath expression. The look up processes is coupled
     * to the implementation
     *
     * @param xPath        an expression to locate the resource
     * @param message      the context object being passed between components of
     *                     the system the rule component is used
     * @param defaultValue default value in the case of there is no resource for the given expression
     * @return resorce corresponded to the given key if there is a resource for the give expression.
     *         Otherwise, the default value should be returned
     */
    public ReturnValue extract(XPath xPath, Object message, Object defaultValue);

    /**
     * Looking up for the default resource. The value of the default resource is coupled to
     * the implementation
     *
     * @param message the context object being passed between components of
     *                the system the rule component is used
     * @return The default resource
     */
    public ReturnValue extractPayload(Object message);

    /**
     * Extracts the envelope of the message
     *
     * @param message the context object being passed between components of
     *                the system the rule component is used
     * @return the envelope of the message
     */
    public ReturnValue extractEnvelope(Object message);

    /**
     * Enrich the context message with the given object based on the given key.
     * The enrichment process is coupled to the implementation
     *
     * @param key     an identifier for the resource
     * @param message the context object being passed between components of
     *                the system the rule component is used
     * @param value   data to be used for enriching context message
     */
    public void enrich(String key, Object message, Object value);
}      
    </pre>

<p><strong>Step 3</strong> : Using Rules Component </p>

<p></p>
<pre xml:space="preserve">// Creating Rule Engine Instance 
RuleEngine  ruleEngine = ruleServerManager.createRuleEngine(classLoader);

// registering a rule set 
String bindURI = ruleEngine.addRuleSet(ruleSetDescription);

// creating a Session to be used to access rule engine runtime
SessionDescription sessionDescription = // get or create 
sessionDescription.setRuleSetURI(bindURI);
Session session = ruleEngine.createSession(sessionDescription);

// to adapt facts from a message. This is optional
InputManager  inputManager = ruleServerManager.createInputManager(getFactDescriptions(), interceptor); 
List&lt;Object&gt; facts = inputManager.processInputs(msgCtx);

// to execute the rules 
List results = session.execute(facts);

// to process results. This is optional
OutputManager outputManager = ruleServerManager.createOutputManager(getResultsDescriptions(),interceptor);
outputManager.processOutputs(results, msgCtx);     
    </pre>

<p>Note: The ruleServerManager is the RuleServerManagerService OSGI service. The
ruleServerManager, outputManager and inputManager should be created once
(Otherwise can be a minor performance issue). </p>
</body>
</html>
